<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The late prints for a standing army and in vindication of the militia consider'd, are in some parts reconcil'd.</title>
            <author>Orme, Thomas, d. 1716.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53430</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O435</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223777</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99834056</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99834056</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38535</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53430)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38535)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1838:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The late prints for a standing army and in vindication of the militia consider'd, are in some parts reconcil'd.</title>
                  <author>Orme, Thomas, d. 1716.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to Thomas Orme.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Armies --  Organization --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Militia --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38535:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Late PRINTS for a Standing Army, AND IN VINDICATION OF THE MILITIA CONSIDER'D, Are in ſome parts Reconcil'd.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Facile eſt inventis addere.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, 1698.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:38535:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:38535:2"/>
            <head>THE Late PRINTS for a Standing Army, AND IN Vindication of the MILITIA conſidered, are in ſome parts reconcil'd.</head>
            <p>I Shall avoid all Prefatory Inſinuations, becauſe Prefaces and Dedications are proper for Books and New Matter, which may bring Honour to the Patron, and Intereſt to the Author. This is merely according to the Title of a Pamphlet vamp'd up with ſome Obſervations that are perchance more plain than the ingenious Writings of ſeveral accurate Pens in Diſcourſes rather Notional than Practical, concerning Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia's and Standing Armies, which are now the general Talk of the Town, and ſeem to have come to high Debates. I hope the Paſſions are over, the Pens having evacuated their Vinegar and Gall, and the Soldier ſheathing his Sword, and confining his Tongue a little cloſer than the warmth of his Blood would at firſt permit. For as an eminent Writer ſays, <hi>Time aſſwages Grief and Anger, which Paſſions Nature is too ſubject unto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is no wonder the King ſhould be uneaſie to part with his Army, or his Soldiers unwilling to be ſeparated from him; for they may be reſembled to Lovers, that came not together without the permiſſion and advice of Friends on both ſides, and ſuch as prompted them to Courage, Amity and Unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, for carrying on ſo great a Work, as to free Us from the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:38535:3"/>diſmal Apprehenſions of Popery, Slavery and Arbitrary Power, which gathered ſo thick a Cloud round about Us, that we were in deſpair of ever ſeeing the glorious Sun-ſhine of Peace, and in fear that that darling Child would never have given Us the Opportunity of ſinging the Song of <hi>Simeon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If his Majeſty had not been inſpired with unſpeakable Valour and Conduct, and his Soldiers with a ſuitable Courage and Affection, it would have rais'd a Wonder, which no Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory has yet afforded a parallel, that ſo great an Army ſhould continue Seven Years, and more, without any the uſual En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements of War, and hardly their common Pay, or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Subſiſtance; ſo that before they have cleared their Hands and Faces, and refreſh'd themſelves after ſuch Fatigues as our Bodies cannot well bear, beſides the Hazards undergone, for avoiding of which we would have given our All, now on a ſudden to be Commanded home to ſeek for a Livelihood, is
<hi>durus Sermo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The great Queſtion is, Whether a competent Number of the preſent diſciplin'd Forces are not abſolutely neceſſary, until the Militia and Train'd Bands are made uſeful: And ſince I am entred into the Query, which all the Writers I have yet met with upon this Subject upon this Seſſions have not ſpoke to ſatisfactorily; I deſire to ſay for my ſelf, that though I am unwilling to give a poſitive Determination, in ſo critical a matter as the event only in proceſs of time ſhall render either of the Councils ſafe and honourable; yet I am not fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to put into the Boat for an endeavour to Trim, knowing my own Innocency from deſigns of Advantage. I as heartily wiſh the Honour and Safety of my Country, as thoſe that expreſs themſelves in a better Stile, and can appear in a better Figure: Therefore being ſenſible of my Defects, I never intended to ſet Pen to paper on this Affair, until I was call'd to in the Verge of the Court, and Queried what was become of ſome Obſervations I had formerly made upon the Militia, which may be a ſort of an Apology for ſcribling on a Subject ſo well handled by great Hiſtorians, who have ſaid all that can be ſaid, both as to the Inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies of a Standing Army, and alſo that the Militia and Train'd Bands have been the only Guards of this Iſland, and other Countries. And tho' the Art and Methods of War are become intricate and political, and our Neighbours are<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38535:3"/>more powerful and formidable than formerly, yet it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, a Militia (in a great meaſure) may be made effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al for our Defence, being guarded on the Borders with ſuch a Naval Strength as the Parliament have thought fit to Vote, yet, with ſubmiſſion, I have not found, or met with any Scheme, or Propoſitions, how, or in how long time the Militia ſhall be ſo uſeful, as that the Army may be forthwith reduced to ſo ſmall a Number as was in 1680.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs it's the height of my Ambition to be thought, and as much as I am able to prove my ſelf, a Lover of the Conſtitution of my Country, the Laws and Cuſtoms of which, I have ſome little knowledge of, yet not ſo fully as I ought, and am not unwilling, or think my ſelf too Old to learn, therefore have endeavoured to read and conſider, all that has yet come out in this Meeting of Parliament, where I doubt not before their Riſing, they will hit upon the beaſt means for the ſecurity of the Kingdom in general, with the Honour and Safety of the Crown, and the Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Liberty and Property, of every individual Subject; ſo that the old Struglings betwixt the Prerogatives of the Crown, and the Privileges of the People, may not be again contended for, or ſo much as Jealouſie rais'd about them: For prevention of which, for the future, I hope it may not be thought a vain Repetition, to recite what Sir <hi>John Denham</hi> ſays in his Poem call'd <hi>Coopers-Hill.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thus Kings by graſping more than they could hold,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Firſt by Oppreſſion made their Subjects bold;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And Popular Sway by forcing Kings to give,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>More than was fit for Subjects to receive;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Run to the like Extream, Both by Exceſs.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For being greater make each other leſſ.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>The King and People are near in Simile to Man and Wife' who ought to help each others Defects, and rejoyce at every thing they are ſucceſsful in; I praiſe God for the diſpoſition I have in rejoycing in this happy, and, I doubt not, laſting Peace, and then I am ſure it is Honourable, and may he be Anathematized that diſturbs it, or endeavours to foment a Jealouſie betwixt the King and his People: The Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> laid a Curſe upon thoſe that offer'd at a Separation: So long as the World laſts, their will be Failures in Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments; we ſee it every day in private Families: But<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38535:4"/>when none of the Seven deadly Sins are predominant, its near an Aſſurance thoſe ſtil'd Venial, will not bring ſo great a Puniſhment, as Subverſion, or Ruin. We are here in this Iſland more enclin'd to Cenſuring, than Amendments, tho' we have a general Queſtion modeſtly put.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Quis tam Lincius eſt qui tantis Tenebris nihil offendet.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>It's apparent moſt of Chriſtendom were concerned in building a Bulwark, and making a Confederacy for ſtopping an Univerſal Monarchy; and that at the ſame time we our ſelves had a diſtinct hazard, that is, we had as much, or more fear (as we pretended) of our Religion than Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty, our Religion being Reformed from the reſt of the Confederacy: And yet I think I may ſay few or none of the Confederacy have heapt up ſo great Wealth in their Stations, as ſeveral Subjects of this Nation (not by hazarding their Perſons either by Sea or Land) but by ſtarving the Seamen, and Land Soldiers, and their Wives, by making Exactions for ready Money on the King and his Officers in their Straits, and alſo diſparaging the very beſt Funds the Parliament could think of, or give for Reputation, or Preſervation of the Government: Extortion in no Age, ever come up to the like; <hi>Empſon</hi> and <hi>Dudley, Burton</hi> and <hi>Graham,</hi> were not half ſo notorious in their Stations; ſo that if theſe were ſtrip'd to what they had in
1688. and that given amongſt the Soldiers, and their Perſons left to run the Gauntlet of the Army to be disbanded, and then ſent to Sea to be keel-haul'd till they have drunk as much Salt-water as the poor Women and Children have ſuck'd in brakiſh Tears, it would make the Gratuities, which the Army is in hopes to receive, much more Satisfactory; we have ſuſpected ſome to be Betrayers of the Councils, but its viſible ſeveral have been grinders of the Poor, and Diſpara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of the Government, Stock-Jobbers particularly, who, if not ſeverely Corrected, will Enrol themſelves with the Jews, and ſo in time be more pernicious to the Government (whilſt in Debt) than either Jew or Jeſuit: For there are Laws ſufficient already to take up theſe when ever any Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Magiſtrate, or the Government, thinks fit; This may be thought to be a digreſſive Invective, yet I requeſt it may be conſidered, whether a continued Standing-Army can be kept without Pay: and whether if the Pay muſt be<pb n="5" facs="tcp:38535:4"/>near as great as it has been, the Taxes muſt not be as great; if ſo, how can the increaſe of the Debt be avoided, a full diſcourſe of which would take up time, almoſt to a forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of the main Undertaking, which may be brought under theſe Heads.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> A Conſideration of what Forces are abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary at preſent for Preſervation of his Majeſty's Perſon with Honour and Safety.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> How many ought to be in conſtant Pay and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, for defence of our Forts, and Maritime Towns.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Whether it be not diſcretion, to have ſome ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numeraries always in readineſs, to ſend to our Plantations, in caſe of any Mutinies there; or that they ſhould be in hazard by
<hi>Bucaniers,</hi> or Pirates, or Foreiners, of any kind whatſoever.</p>
            <p>To theſe three Heads I do not apprehend the Militia was ever employ'd, nor do I perceive there's any Thoughts of making the Militia for theſe Purpoſes, nor were they ever naturally Inclin'd to theſe Uſes: Nor do I ſee how they can be Imployed in theſe Affairs; their uſe being Properly,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> To Suppreſs any Inſurrections that ſhall happen within the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> To Convene and march to that part, or Quarter of the Kingdom, where an Invaſion may be ſuſpected.</p>
            <p>For which two Purpoſes laſt mentioned, in my Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the Militia may be as effectually uſeful, as a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Army, ſo large as will be abſolutely neceſſary for that purpoſe; For demonſtration of which I muſt crave a little more Patience of the Reader, and his Liberty to draw ſome Obſervations, wherein a numerous Army may raiſe ſeveral Inconveniencies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> it is apparent a Standing-Army is not allow'd by any of our Neighbours, tho' by their Situation on the Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, they are enforced to maintain great Numbers in Pay, and ſtrict Guards to defend each Precincts, like Shepherds with their Aſſiſtants in common Fields to prevent Streakings and Treſpaſſes, which is a charge and Inconveniency ſaved us, (God be praiſed for his Providence) Nature guarding us with the Sea, which being aſſiſted by humane Endeavours as the Parliament have wiſely conſider'd, I doubt not we are as ſafe as in former Ages; Tho we are told of the great<pb n="6" facs="tcp:38535:5"/>Numbers of the <hi>French,</hi> and the Poſſibilities of their at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting us by Invaſion, which in Human Reaſoning is as remote a Probability as can be propoſed, I do not find they ever attempted it, when they had more promiſing Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities, than I hope they will ever have again; for I am inclined to believe 20 or 30000 Men were in readineſs in 1688, to have come over; but how, after what manner, and upon what Account; not by way of Invaſion but aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, if King
<hi>James</hi> would have helpt them over, and accepted them, which as I have heard he never would. Now, (tho' I underwent as many of his Paſſions and Severities as any one in his Reign) yet ſince I did Eat of his Bread, though it was carefulneſs with Sour Grapes, for I was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed by him of the Imployments I bought in King <hi>Cb.</hi> II. time, yet I will not charge him with more Endeavours for alienating the Affections of his Subjects, than were relly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitated, they were ſufficient to draw Mortification upon him in this World, <hi>Tantum Religio potuit—</hi> But to the diſcourſe we are upon, neither then did they offer to Embark, nor in all this long War, (tho' they took many of our Merchantmen) had they ever Shipping or Men, fit for the purpoſe of an Invaſion: we are told it was an Accident, that prevented the danger we were in, when the <hi>Spaniſh Armada</hi> attempted us.</p>
            <p>This is to draw us into amuſements, and make us conclude our Politicians will always have Miracles or Wonders, on Foot. Where's the Peace if we muſt have more Troops quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd amongſt us than we have had all the War. This looks as if we had been paying Taxes theſe Eight Years for the Aſſiſtance of our Neighbours, and ſo much to the weakning of our ſelves, as that we might be the eaſier conquer'd by our own Conſents. Can it be imagin'd we have a firm Peace, when we ſay and argue the
<hi>French</hi> are in poſſibility and readineſs to invade us? Have we ſhak'd hands with our Neighbours in the Peace, ſo that there is to be no more Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting one from the other? I promiſed my ſelf a firm Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance, during this King's Life, at leaſt; And tho' all our Aſſiſtances may be forgotten of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s time, yet I cannot think its forgotten that we paid them readily and willingly the 600000 l. which was all I ever heard was ask'd for the happy coming in of King
<hi>William.</hi> Nor do I imagine they will not allow their danger all this War to be<pb n="7" facs="tcp:38535:5"/>more to them than us. <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> and many others, have been often attempted, when we were quiet in our Beds. It muſt be confeſs'd we were conſequentially in danger. <hi>Tunc tua res agiter pares cum proxima Ardet.</hi> Our turn no doubt would have been to be attack'd by the <hi>French,</hi> had we not endeavoured to defend the
<hi>Low-Countries,</hi> whoſe ſubmiſſion would have been our Ruine. But I cannot think they will ſuffer the <hi>French</hi> to invade us; for, if we be ruin'd, what will become of them? Theſe Diſcourſes make the Peace but a Ceſſation, and the <hi>French</hi> do their work the ſooner: Theſe are but Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, I fear not the Event. For if Preparations be now great, and all things ready, and a Wind to ſerve their Turn, I cannot avoid thinking that we ſhall not be watchful, and in a poſture of Defence, and that our Neighbours alſo will be wafting over to our Aſſiſtance as readily, and as great Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and with as good affection, (eſpecially if we pay them again) as our Enemies have malice, whom we ſay are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd to ſuch poverty, they were not able to Cultivate their Country, and neceſſitated to court our King to a Peace: And yet on the ſudden we have a formidable Scheme of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſions. We have had in former Reigns 40000 Black Bills to deſtroy us. In the Revolution every individual Perſon in fear of being murthered by the <hi>Iriſh;</hi> and now we ſhall be in daily fear of the <hi>French,</hi> if we have not a Standing Army to defend us. Nor do we think, that if the <hi>French</hi> do not come immediately to us, that our other Neighbours will be more afraid of our coming to them. If our Trading hold or increaſe, I am near an aſſurance we may as ſoon Tranſport, as be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded: And if we neither Aggreſs abroad, nor be Invaded at home, its concluſive a Standing Eſtabliſhed Army is to give Laws at home; and then Old <hi>England</hi> good night altogether.</p>
            <p>For my part, I ſhall never be in fear of an Invaſion, whilſt we rely on God's Providence, and are awake to uſe Human Reaſoning and Endeavours. But allow our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours have attempted raſh Things; therefore, ſhall we nurſe up unadviſed or non-preſidented Policies, which may be like Worms in Children that eat their Intrails? Is a ſupernume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary Army to be kept up for meer Fantaſms? Did ever a ſupernumerary Servant or two kept idle in a Family, do half ſo much good at a Chance-time, as his Idleneſs did hurt in the general?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:38535:6"/>I hope in time of Peace we ſhall not be infatuated into Blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Careleſneſs, and Effeminacy; but ſhall have a Natural and Political Care, keeping our Arms from ruſting, and our Shipping ready to ſail. And our Ambaſſadors will be watchful: And if we have not Spies, I hope we have Friends, that, like Starlings to the Dove-Houſe, will communicate to us when any Great Deſign is upon Us. 'Tis confeſs'd, the King came over with a ſmall Number; yet King <hi>James</hi> had Intimation of them; and the Preparations were examin'd, how cloſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Deſign was cover'd. And altho there was never a more General Inclination here, or Invitation and Preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for his Reception; yet we ſee croſs Winds retarded him once; and it was a Wonder, next to a Miracle, that he ſhould ſtretch ſo long a Sea, at that Seaſon, and to a Place which was the beſt and only one he could have been ſucceſsful in; and yet we have heard it was come very near a Reſolution of Returning, tho no Army did or could come near to oppoſe Him.</p>
            <p>To keep a number of Men for conſumption meerly of the Product, is like the Lubbards in Monaſteries heretofore; and if that is the main of the Argument, 'tis requiſite they ſhould have parallel Cloiſters, or Cells, and the like Reſtraints to keep them within compaſs: For 'tis apparent, thoſe we have had idle in Nurſeries for this War, have made horrid incurſions into the Civil Rights, by ſtreaking and making themſelves Maſters of all the Game in every Royalty they came near; and have not only broke into all Immoralities, and ſo voraciouſly and prodigally waſted and devour'd their Landlords; whereby that Revenue it ſelf that ſhould pay them and their Quarters, is much ſhortned, and will be more; for the Roads will not be paſſable; and in all roads the Accommodations are very indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, many Publick Houſes being ſhut up.
'Tis a ſad ſtory to reckon how many have been Murder'd, and how Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy has been affronted. An Army is to be always buſied either in their proper Exerciſes, or Works Military; or having leiſure from them, if they were employ'd in cutting Rivers, or making or mending Highways, they would be fitter for Fatigues in marching, or their own proper Buſineſs.</p>
            <p>I hope Employments will be found for thoſe that may be thought abſolutely neceſſary to be kept on foot at preſent, even thoſe that are or ſhall be thought neceſſary for Guards about this great Town; which, I confeſs, I think ought to be more<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38535:6"/>than was in 80, for ſeveral Reaſons as I may inſtance here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after: And alſo Publick Works in the Frontiers and Garriſons, will keep the Soldiers in Health, and make them digeſt what's wholeſome Diet in their Quarters. I go not upon the diſtinct Number of Veteran Troops, or Companies, becauſe I do not find any certain Number inſiſted upon: Yet I hope I may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, That if this Magnificent City ſpreads her Wings propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionably in Times of Peace, as ſhe has done in the Times of Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies and Fears of having her Cuſtoms and Privileges en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croach'd upon, and in danger of being ſubverted; and as ſhe has done even in this long War, her Streets being much encreas'd and peopled to the Weſt and North, and this principally by Foreiners, who are likely to encreaſe wonderfully more in times of Peace. Not that I would ſay any thing to put a ſtop to the Scripture's Declaration, notwithſtanding that the Numbers of the People are the Honour of the King, and cauſes Induſtry in a Nation; yet, I ſay, if the Numbers encreaſe by Shoals of Foreiners, we muſt either have them abſolutely in the Boundaries of our Laws, or have Sentinels ſet over them, or Regiments particularly Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd amongſt them.</p>
            <p>Pardon me if I am miſtaken, when I ſay, I do not believe the Train'd Bands can prevent an Inſurrection there, whenever any Preſſure, or Caprichio, ſhould diſpoſe them to combine; I do believe Wives and Children, and a ſettled Habitation, go a great way towards a Security. But if
<hi>France</hi> be ſo formidable, as that 'tis prudent or neceſſary to watch for keeping them out, I ſhall be inclin'd to conclude, 'tis as requiſite to have a careful eye upon thoſe of that Nation amongſt us: For I am morally aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, <hi>England</hi> was never invaded, without a Party within who gave an Invitation. 'Tis confeſs'd, the City within the Walls may be kept in Safety and Obedience, by the Diſcretion of the Lord Mayor and his Lieutenancy, and may march out with their Train'd-Bands and Auxiliaries, to join with the Military Force of <hi>Middleſex.</hi> But the Foreiners, if combin'd, may be embody'd and form'd and fix'd in ſuch advantageous Poſts, as one ſhall find it a difficult matter to attack or ſubdue them; eſpecially if the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is conſternated with an Invaſion. And I am ſorry there is ſo apparent an occaſion to fear, that we have too many of our own Natives, that are ſo far from dutiful Principles, that they care not how great the Devaſtation is, ſo that they may ſhare the Shipwreck.
<hi>Plutarch</hi> was not miſtaken in ſaying,</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>When Diſcord rules in Realm or Town,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Wicked gain the Chief Renown.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:38535:7"/>By this time I think my ſelf concluded to have changed my Mind, and adhere to the Arguments for a Standing Army, when in reality I am only for requiſite and neceſſary Guards in and about this City, the Maritim Towns and Sea-Ports, beſides a Reſerve for our Plantations; I wiſh not one Man more: For I do not think there needs one Troop, or Company, throughout the Body of the Kingdom: I do really think the Militia may be made ſo uſeful, as to ſecure the Government from any Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection there. And to demonſtrate I am not for a numerous Force in continu'd Pay and Quarters; by permiſſion, as the part of the City I have mentioned may reaſonably require, I humbly offer this as a rational Propoſition; tho' I am ſure it will be arraign'd at firſt fight, if ever it be allow'd of, or effected (becauſe it was debated, and came near a Determination in the Reigns of King <hi>Charles</hi> and King <hi>James</hi>) that is, Building a Citadel where the <hi>Mews</hi> is; which has room alſo to make Barracks to contain a greater number than are abſolutely neceſſary; and a few Cannon planted there, will awe all that part of the Town, better than ſeveral Regiments diſtributed in Quarters. And moreover, if Regiments be lodg'd by Reliefs for a Fortnight, three Weeks, or a Month, at diſcretion,; they are readier for the Guards, and leſs troubleſome to the City, by coming and going through all parts to and from the Parade, and in leſs danger than formerly of being indicted for a Nuſance. This may ſeem a chimerical Notion, coming from a private Perſon; and if it ſhould be entertain'd and ſet about, without the Advice or Approbation of the Parliament, it would perhaps raiſe great Jealouſies and Fears: For avoiding of which, I ſhall no longer inſiſt upon that Thought.</p>
            <p>Therefore let us now enter into a Diſcourſe how the Militia may be made uſeful, and far exceed the Number of all the Army now in Pay, with abundantly leſs Charge to the Nation, than the Army has been, and muſt of neceſſity be, till the Militia is made ſerviceable; which muſt be firſt by Acts of Parliament; and thoſe brought into Methods and Exerciſe, which will require Time; for Soldiers are not made by Inſpiration, as ſome Pulpita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians are; Military Men muſt have Diſcipline and Exerciſe to make them uſeful. And I doubt it will require more than one Year to make Acts, and put them in practice, ſo as that they ſhall have the intended effect: And till then, I do not believe any Man will think it neceſſary, through Jealouſie, to have the King and Government naked.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:38535:7"/>Some Men think 'tis no more than to ſay (now the Peace is concluded) <hi>To your Tents, O Iſrael—</hi> I wiſh thoſe Perſons would conſider, that if we were as morally aſſur'd as is poſſible, that neither Foreiners from abroad, nor at home, would think of diſturbing us; What a Condition would our innate Diſpoſition bring us to, if the King ſhould ſuddenly die (which God forbid) and no Guard for the ſucceeding Government, but the preſent confus'd Militia! I have known the Militia themſelve very near Battling for a Father and a ſpurious, or at leaſt a controverted Son. Our Diviſions, Subdiviſions, and Animoſities, would make mad Work: We ſhould be ſuddenly like an <hi>Aceldama;</hi> which ſad Omen GOD avert.</p>
            <p>I am as willing as any Man to hide our own Infirmities; but as Forein States pry as much as they can into our Politicks; ſo no doubt they look into our Morals.</p>
            <p>I hope I may be pardon'd if I think the King is us'd in this our Iſland, as we our ſelves are with our Air and Agues, ſometimes very hot, and immediately very cold: One while we admire him, and exalt Him to the Station of a God, and in an inſtant, ſo ſoon as Safety appears, before the Proclamation of Peace is out of our Ears, and our Addreſſes deliver'd, we are inflam'd with Jealouſie, and fear Our Eagle will ſoar ſo high in the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine of his Proſperity, that he will make ſome ſudden
<hi>Cancellere</hi> upon us. I would not be bold with the Royal Hawks, nor the Noble Game; yet I hope I may, like a Sparrow-Hawk, have a ſhort flight at the Buſh, by hinting at what has been printed: For there was a Book that made a Great Man more than a Conquerour; and there has been Clauſes that ſeem to make him leſs than a Man: For after a large Declaration of a Free Gift, follows Clauſes of Reſtrictions that makes our HERO leſs than an
<hi>Imberbis Juvenis,</hi> who has power to diſpoſe of what his God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers gave him. Disbanding and Manacling was not thought of, when Fears of Popery, Arbitrary Power, and Acts of Reſumption crouded into our Apprehenſions.</p>
            <p>It was ſaid the laſt Year, That if there were not ſetled ſome laſting Security for thoſe that had brought in their Money freely, the Money'd Men, and the Military, would find, in Peace, delatory Conſiderations; perhaps both one Anſwer, <hi>Look to your Hits better the next time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have one certain Obſervation in <hi>England,</hi> That the Soldier who makes not his Fortune whilſt the Sword is in his hand,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:38535:8"/>ſhall have no more than a Complemental Commendation; for in a ſhort time of Peace, and old Soldier will be like an old Almanack.</p>
            <p>It may be freely wager'd, there's not one Man in a hundred that charges his Memory with the Fears he had in the Revolution, of an
<hi>Iriſh-man</hi>'s cutting his Throat, though there was not above 3000 to do this all over <hi>England;</hi> perhaps not much above 48 Hours before the Town of <hi>Berwick,</hi> Cape of <hi>Cornwal, Dover</hi>-Peer, and
<hi>Holy-head,</hi> had theſe diſmal Apprehenſions.</p>
            <p>But that we may not always continue in this <hi>Dilemma,</hi> I would humbly offer theſe Two Expedients towards making the Militia more uſeful:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> By ſhortning their Numbers: And,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> By lengthning their Time for Marchings and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe.</p>
            <p>And for ſhortning their Numbers; whereas by a moderate Computation they may amount in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> to 90, or
100000 Men: (tho' at the full Value of the Lands and other Eſtates they ought to amount to 150000) Reduce them to half, that is about 50000: And this will be done by flinging off Quarters of Horſes, and ſmall Contributers to Foot; which cauſes great Diſturbances, and is one reaſon ſo oft New Men and Horſes appear. But if an entire 500 l. <hi>per Ann.</hi> finds a Horſe and Horſe-man, and 50 l. <hi>per Ann.</hi> finds a Foot-man; they will the eaſiler continue the ſame Man, and the ſame Horſe, or very good Reaſon will be ſhew'd to the Lieutenancy or other Officers: And they may be the more ſtrictly oblig'd ſo to do, and with leſs clamour and trouble fined and be diſtrain'd upon for Defaults.</p>
            <p>Perhaps mentioning this part of the Militia-Laws may affright ſome from reading the remainder of this Diſcourſe, therefore let us a little conſider the Conſtitution of the Nation, when the Military Force was ſo uſeful as to be our abſolute Security. I think Knights Service was the compoſition of thoſe Military Forces now commonly call'd Militia: Which demonſtrates, that Maſters themſelves appearing in Perſon for defence of their Country, Families, and Eſtates, were much better than their Servants, of which the Militia now ſeems to be compoſed which is a Miſtake in practice contrary to the Intention when Knights-Service was taken away. For when the Crown and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment comply'd to give eaſe to the Gentry and Freeholder, they<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38535:8"/>thought it a Hardſhip and Slavery to appear in their Perſons, being a Fatigue they could not bear, unleſs they were of more robuſt Conſtitutions, than they generally were when this was conſider'd and comply'd with. Then came the Militia to be compos'd of Repreſentatives.</p>
            <p>Now it was not ſuſpected, that thoſe who had been thus indulg'd by the Government, would ever have been ſo remiſs in ſending ſuch ſlight and ſhagrene Men and Horſes, for the Defence of the Crown and Government, and their own Perſons and Properties. And this Inconſiderateneſs, in a long Series of Peace, was the firſt cauſe of ſlighting of the Militia, and caus'd the Crown and Court to ſeek for further Aſſiſtance. And now the Crown is guarded by a Military Aſſiſtance, which it confides in, 'tis natural and good Reaſon to keep what looks like a Certainty, inſtead of what is generally allow'd not to have the Face or Body of Security. But yet the Conſtitution is not ſo much deſtroy'd, but that 'tis probable it may be recover'd to its former Reputation; and that's what every <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> and Lover of the Country and Government ought to endeavour for. Therefore let us go on to draw Propoſitions for making them uſeful; and as that appears, I doubt not, the King will be inclin'd to leſſen thoſe which we will now only call neceſſary Guards, and not what we now, by an affrighting Expreſſion, call a Standing Army. I would diſtinguiſh betwixt permiſſion for Conveniency, or Neceſſity, and that which is fear'd to be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd; which I am fully aſſur'd the Parliament will never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to, but will be their Buſineſs every Seſſion, to ſee how theſe Penſionary Soldiers may be leſſen'd — Jealouſies ſtarted are not eaſily ſtifled. 'Tis Time that muſt make the Militia uſeful; for which we will go on, upon the computation of 50000 Horſe and Foot in <hi>England</hi> and
<hi>Wales.</hi> For bringing theſe to be uſeful, let us ſee how an Act may be drawn, keeping as near as may be to thoſe Acts we have now in being. Firſt, The limited time of fourteen Days in the Year, ſeems neceſſary to be enlarg'd: For ſourteen Days in the Year for Private and General Muſters ſeems too little, when half their time is ſpent in their going to the Rendezvous, or private Meeting, which ſometimes are long Marches; or if ill Weather, there's either want of Refreſhment, or they diſabled for Exerciſe, that their Meeting ſignifies little more than the expence of Money.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:38535:9"/>I do promiſe my ſelf the Number will be ſooner conſented to, than the neceſſary time I think to propoſe; though I will not deſire the enlargement of fourteen Days in the Year, unleſs it be upon extraordinary Occaſions, more than once in four Years: For I would propoſe, that 20000 Men ſhould be march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every Year to
<hi>Hounſlow,</hi> or ſuch Place as the King thinks fit, and there encamp for a Month or ſix Weeks; which time of marching out of their reſpective Countries, will improve them to ſuch a heighth of natural Inclination, that they will appear thereby more uſeful, than in twenty Years meeting according to the preſent Acts. And encamping may make up eight or ten Weeks; and this coming but once in four Years, will not be ſo great a Charge, as many may ſuppoſe at firſt ſight: For con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering here's much of the number reduc'd, and tho' I propos'd that 500 <hi>l. per Ann.</hi> ſhall find a Man, Horſe, and Accoutrements, and 50 <hi>l. per Ann.</hi> a Footman, for ſecuring or preventing Changes of Men and Horſes; yet it is not intended they ſhall be at the whole Charge, and others ſpar'd.</p>
            <p>I the rather propoſe <hi>Hounſlow</hi> as the moſt convenient, not only for the Goodneſs of its Situation, but its nearneſs to
<hi>London,</hi> whereby it might eaſily be accommodated out of this Majeſty's Stores in the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> with Tents, Arms, and Field Pieces: And if His Majeſty would add thereto (at his own Charge) Ammunition-bread, it would be a mighty eaſe to the Country. I know I am enter'd into a Propoſition that will be nicely and ſtrictly canvaſs'd; becauſe I ſuppoſe every individual Perſon that has been tax'd to this War, either for Lands, Money, Offices, or Perſonal Eſtate, ſhall bear a proportion to the Charge of maintaining the <hi>Militia</hi> of their County or City: For I do not apprehend where the Subject-Matter is of that Nature, that every individual Perſon enjoys a Benefit, why that Perſon ſhould not pay proportionably to his Advantage and Eſtate</p>
            <p>I confeſs it has been my own Inclination all this War, that the Charge ſhould have been born and maintain'd by a General Exciſe: It will be told me immediately, this is a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth Expedient, and Forein Practice, enſlaving the People, and eating and drinking by weight and meaſure, giving ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Perſons the Privilege of examining my Cellar and Larder, and a greater Publication and Recording of my Houſe-keeping, than the
<hi>Spaniards</hi> ſcattering the Feathers at his Door when he eats a Fowl. Upon Examination, the Argument will be found<pb n="15" facs="tcp:38535:9"/>as light as the Simile: For if you examine the Laws that have been, and are in force at this Minute, you will find your ſelf as narrowly inſpected, as a general Exciſe will reach; eſpecially if you have the ſame liberty in a general Exciſe, as you now have in the Malt-Act; that is, to compound it at ſo much a Head for your Family; and then all your Generoſity of Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeping, and Killing your own Meat, runs in; you oblige your Tenants, weaker ſort of Neighbours; or being hoſpitable to the Poor, or Travellers, coſts you nothing extraordinary; and yet 'tis as advantageous to them.</p>
            <p>This would make a long Digreſſion (if I ſhould purſue it) from the main Topick; eſpecially if I ſhould endeavour to ſilence another general Out-cry, <hi>Oh! this is deſtructive to the Freedom and Happineſs of Old</hi> England! I wiſh I could ſee Old <hi>England</hi> truly ſtated; I confeſs I have drank Her Health a hundred times, or more; and yet I can only admire Her, as I do Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in a Farthingal and Ruff. I deſire to know where the Honour of Old <hi>England</hi> reſided undiſturb'd, when the Act of Chimney-Money paſt: I am ſure She was not free from ordinary Viſitants, either in Her Rooms of State, or Cloſets; for Cloſets, a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, I am ſure, (and I think a Peeper) might demand a view. The reach of your preſent Laws for the Militia, ſhall enforce you to diſcover to 20<hi>s.</hi> what you are worth, or elſe you ſhall forſwear your ſelf, or bear that Burthen that neither an Old nor Young
<hi>Engliſh-man</hi> would bear, if he could help it. The Law and matter of Fact is this: The Lord-Lieutenants, with their Deputies, or any Three of them, may charge you or me to Horſe or Foot as they pleaſe; and you muſt comply accordingly, or ſwear to the Eſtimate of your Condition. Now in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Taxes, 'tis in the breaſt of an Aſſeſſor to return in his Duplicate, what Summ he pleaſes to the Commiſſioners, to whom you may appeal. What then? Your Remedy will not be had without an Oath. The Commiſſioners themſelves are to withdraw, whilſt they are aſſeſſed by their Brethren; who if miſtaken in their Eſtimate, it muſt be born, or elſe Swearing muſt remedy the Miſtake. And this leads me to a Queſtion of the difference betwixt our Old and New <hi>England:</hi> In the Old the Oath <hi>ex Officio;</hi> in the New, Oaths <hi>Purgative</hi> or <hi>Defenſive.</hi> The matter is, Whether is <hi>England</hi> the worſe for altering or adding ſome few Particulars and Clauſes, for making her Militia more uſeful? Are we the worſe for reforming the Church in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:38535:10"/>
               <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. 's time? Are we the worſe for pulling down or demoliſhing inland Caſtles and Strong Holds? And upon the unfortunate Burning the City, would you have had it Built in the ſame Form as before? 'Tis now much better, and 'tis <hi>London</hi> ſtill, the ſame Ground; and St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s is where it was.</p>
            <p>If I have gain'd the Argument in that Point, I ſhall go more cheerfully on, and prove my Poſition in the Title; that 'tis an eaſie matter to add to the Foundations of Buildings or Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and ſometimes Alterations are made very advantageous in the Walls of old Buildings.</p>
            <p>As to this Standard of the Militia, I would have it a Militia ſtill, and that it ſhould have the ſame full Force, Strength, and Virtue that it ever had; and if a Red-Coat, or another Colour, will do the ſame thing as a Head-piece, Back, Breaſt, Cap-a-peé; why ſhould Men be bruized to death with carrying of furr'd Iron, to the tiring and ſpoiling of their Horſes alſo; eſpecially when 'tis one of the chief Ridicules the Diſciplin'd Army makes upon the Militia? There are many Reflections like thoſe, the Army makes upon the Militia; I have heard moſt of them, and can find Commendation for both Army and Militia, and Defects or Inconveniences in both, having been in both: But not deſpiſing or eſpouſing either, perhaps having not found Pleaſure or Profit in either, longer than the Heat of Youth was in me, I ſhall diſcourſe of them only as they are uſeful to the Government, and People in general, and their joint Intereſt.</p>
            <p>Therefore I come now at laſt to ſtick to Reaſons, why the Militia ſhould be paid by a General Stock, of and in the County, proportionably to the Numbers it ſhall naturally raiſe, according to the computed Numbers now, and the Reducements propos'd, and for the Time and Marches aforemention'd.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the firſt Objection to the Time and Marchings, to be paid by the Country will be here in the Exchequer and for Offices, I muſt declare my ſelf ſo much an <hi>Engliſh man,</hi> as to be bold to ſay, thoſe Offices are more improv'd by this long War, than any Employments or Lands in <hi>England;</hi> not that I envy them (if they are not ill Men, as has been hinted at) for I would have had one of the Places my ſelf: But I am apt to believe the Country may ſave Money, and the King be as well ſerv'd. So the King be faithfully and well ſerv'd, 'tis equal to him whether the Officers and Soldiers in the Militia be paid by Methods which ſhall be directed by Parliament for payments in the Countries, or the General Pay-Offices, as it has been this late War.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:38535:10"/>Firſt 'Tis certain Money may be ſav'd, which Offices and Officers will ſwallow. The Freeholder deſires to ſee who ſpends the Money he compaſſes by turning the Plow at the Lands-end.
'Tis fine following the Plow in a Sun-ſhine Day, ſucking in, and ſnuffing up the Freſhneſs of the Farth, but Wet and Dry to follow and turn the Plow;
<hi>Hic Labor, hoc Opus eſt!</hi> And after all your Nine Months Labour carking and caring, you muſt Thraſh out your Compenſation. Will not this naturally make a Man enquire who eats and drinks his 4<hi>s.</hi> in the Pound out of the Quick Stock?</p>
            <p>This will raiſe a Diſpoſition for making the Militia uſeful, if it be ſo methodiz'd, that at the Aſſizes, or Seſſions, every Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable may bring back the Officers and Soldiers Pay who lives within his Liberties, without Poundage, Agencies, and ſeveral other ſtoppages: You will find all the Soldiers that ſhall be disbanded, ſollicit to be in the Militia, and wiſh they may march to
<hi>Hounſlow.</hi> It will be found that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation is not ſo effeminate, ſluggiſh, cowardly, or indiſpos'd to Military Affairs, as they have been character'd perhaps by Three Potentates, who have made uſe of their Travels to dazle their Deſign of altering the Fundamental Part of the Government, which I heartily adhere to; tho' I am not ſtrictly for a
<hi>Spaniſh Formidon,</hi> who runs the hazard of twenty Inconveniencies for an inconſiderable old Cuſtom.</p>
            <p>But now it pleaſes Providence to afford us the Proſpect of a happy and peaceable New Year, let us endeavour to pick out of the Times paſt, what's rationally probable to ſecure future Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, from the Calamities theſe latter have undergone: To which purpoſe, let us go on to make our Diſcipline equal to our Courage, which has appear'd in the Eyes, and has had the due Character, from the Jedgment and Pronuncition of the Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and moſt Experienc'd General in Chriſtendom, our preſent KING.</p>
            <p>There ſeems to be an abſolute neceſſity, that ſomething ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial ſhould be done concerning the Militia. I am not ſo fond of my own Poſitions as to preſs for their obſervance: I only ſet them out as marks for others to try their Guns againſt: But if they ſhould be ſo fortunate as to come within the View and Cognizance of his Majeſty and Parliament, and they give any ſort of Countenance, it may encourage me to a further Induſtry and Explanation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:38535:11"/>Should what has been ſaid as to Numbers, Times and Places, be put in practice for four Years, I doubt not it will be found a very good Expedient for making the Militia uſeful; and conſequently a ſatisfactory way for ſecuring the Nation. 'Tis not to be imagin'd, before
'tis practic'd, how much it will Spirit the Nation, when the Maſculine Martial Diſpoſition ſhall be aſſur'd they are to appear before ſo Great a General as we have mention'd; whoſe ſcrutinous Eye in Marchings or Muſterings, is the ſtricteſt Superiour that our <hi>England</hi> has been bleſt with: And I hope, when he ſees an entire Body of <hi>Engliſh</hi> (for I think his Armies hitherto have been a miſcellany of all Nations) he will be fully aſſur'd they will really deſerve that Great and High Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentive Character he has given of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Courage, which, for the Honour of the Nation, the preſent Army has kept up; and I hope the Parliament will reſolve on ſignalizing the Army's Courage Affection before they part. Were I not doubtful my Head and Pen would be thought too buſie, I would humbly offer that an Act ſhould paſs, That every Soldier that has a Certificate from his Officer, That he has behav'd himſelf Faithfully and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rageouſly, ſhall have the Freedom of every City or Town Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate, to ſet up what Manufactory, Trade, or lawful Induſtry his Genius leads him to; or if lame, or ſuper-annuated, to receive a Penſion from his Native Country, or longeſt Reſidence before he went for a Soldier. There was ſomething of this kind, upon the Reſtoration of King <hi>Charles,</hi> when there was alſo a Proviſion made for Officers, which happily may be now. But I hope there will be more care taken for a ſpeedier Diſtribution; for the Sollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and Attendance eat out the Benevolence. And if there be now an Act, as there was then, for prohibiting the diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing People by Characters, it would take off many Heats that ariſe, and may encreaſe a better Affection in the Nation.</p>
            <p>I hope theſe Notions are not erroneous, tho' they deviate a little from the main Subject; to which I crave leave to put another Patch, by way of Caution, that this Method for the Militia be not expenſive by the way of vying; for I am near an Aſſurance, that if the Poſition of coming to
<hi>Hounſlow</hi> take effect, if there be not a limitation for Clothing and Equipage, both of Officers and Soldiers, the Counties, and Officers in each County, will be vying who ſhall appear moſt ſplendid before his Majeſty: For 'tis not to be doubted his Martial Diſpoſition will Honour them often with his Preſence. It will be a Recreation to Him at
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:38535:11"/>that Seaſon of the Year I humbly propoſe, from
<hi>May</hi>-Day to <hi>Midſummer,</hi> which in probability will be healthful and pleaſant Marching and Encamping, and a Seaſon the Soldiers may be beſt ſpar'd from their Countries, returning by Harveſt. It will be a time the King, Nobility, and Gentry may want Buſineſs and Recreation, which makes them dote on the Wells: For the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, 'tis probable, will be ſeldom ſitting about that time; nor is there Field-Sports for the King, Nobility, or Gentry; nor has the Country Gentleman much to do at that Seaſon. Yet 'tis pity a Gentleman that loves his Country and is willing to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow his Pains, and hazard his Life, ſhould ſuffer in his Eſtate, either by neglecting it, or being at an extraordinary Expence: Therefore for a diſtinguiſhing Mark of Honour, and ſomething of Intereſt, let him be exempted from other chargeable Offices; if he himſelf will plead the Act, that is, from being High Sheriff, ſerving on Juries, or being a Juſtice of Peace, &amp;<hi>c.</hi> But I would be underſtood all Commiſſion-Officers, under a Deputy Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; as, Colonels, Lieutenant Colonels, Majors, Captains, Lieutenants, and Enſigns. As for other Field-Officers, Lieutenant-Generals, Major-Generals, Brigadiers, &amp;<hi>c.</hi> 'tis not to be doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but the King has nurs'd up a ſufficient number, who have ſhewn their Valour and Conduct in the late War, and will be inſtructive to the Militia, whenever they ſhall appear: And altho' the ſham <hi>Buda</hi> and <hi>Maeſtricht</hi> were ridicul'd in former times; yet if a <hi>Namure</hi> or <hi>Limerick,</hi> or ſeveral Skirmiſhes in the Defiles; ſuch Attacks (as Diverſions) every Year they are encamp'd, will not be found to be loſt Labours.</p>
            <p>This Poſition will help to bring in many of good Eſtates to be the Officers: And if it ſhould ſo happen that ſome Gentlemen out of Modeſty (as there are many very ſtout Gentlemen, ſo modeſt that they will not offer themſelves tho' they are willing) ſhould not voluntarily come in, let it be in the Breſt of the King, His Lord Lieutenants, &amp;<hi>c.</hi> to recommend, invite, and perſwade ſuch Gentlemen as they think proper, but no compulſive Power for Officers: And I have heard ſome argue (when I made ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions formerly for the improvement of the
<hi>Militia</hi>) that it was againſt the Fundamental Conſtitution of
<hi>England,</hi> to have any Man preſs'd; To which Objection was offered, That in caſe a finder is not able, or willing of himſelf to march, or liſt himſelf, nor cannot enjoin a Son, or prevail with a Relation, or a young Neighbour, that's fit and likely to be a Repreſentative,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:38535:12"/>in ſuch a Caſe, if the Finder diſcovers a fitting Man in the Pariſh or Neighbourhood, that in his Opinion and in the Opinion of his ſubſtantial Neighbours, and of the Parſon of the Pariſh, who may certifie under their Hands, That ſuch a Perſon is able, and in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Appearance fitting for Soldiery; and that it does not appear to them, that this Perſon does get his Livelihood by an open, indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Means, but it is to be fear'd he is a Treſpaſſer in the Night, or at improper times out upon Fiſhing, Fowling, Shooting Deer or Rabbits, if not other worſe things: Upon ſuch Information to the next Juſtice of Peace, he may ſend his Warrant for him and enjoin him to liſt himſelf; and, in caſe of refuſal, he may ſend him to the Houſe of Correction, or the Goal for 12 Months, or till ſuch time as he will liſt himſelf; I am ſure it would have eas'd the Country of many idle Perſons, that have come to the Gallows, and yet would not put themſelves into Arms all this War.</p>
            <p>Theſe are but Particles of the Diſcourſe may ariſe, betwixt the Conſtitution and the Modalities; which ſeems to me like the Carpet-Knights, that arraign that which they either dare not do themſelves, or if they have a Family-Courage to undertake, they know not how to do; yet to do ſomething more than Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is <hi>Ajax</hi> to <hi>Ulyſſes, Oſtente Facta:</hi> And we have a new Pronunciator, rather do ill than do nothing; which is, if you will do nothing by way of a ſerious Conſideration to make the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia</hi> uſeful, you muſt ſubmit to a Standing Army, which will do little miſchievous Tricks, whilſt they are idle, and groſſer as Time ſerves: I can and dare witneſs, that I heard it in an Argument of ſeveral Officers in a Veterane Regment now in being, That if the King commanded him to take the Life of any Man, he would do it ſubſervient to his Pay; and this Topick was currently diſcours'd amongſt ſeveral Officers upon the Trial of <hi>Urats.</hi> Theſe will in part hint, I am not abſolutely a Stranger to my Country, nor affected to any thing that ſhall in common Senſe be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial; therefore give me leave to go through one Alluſion, and I have done: Here's King and Parliament, Subjects, Civil and Military, Military ſtanding Army, or <hi>Militia,</hi> who labour, gather, and ſpin, like Bees and Silk-worms, for the Publick Good. Now as Bees and Silk-worms are mixt with Drones, Waſps and Grubs; ſo the Conſtitution being a mixt Government, it ſeems reaſonable the Preſervation ſhould be a Miſcellany between a <hi>Militia,</hi> and Regular Troops. This Alluſion is an Epitome of the whole Diſcourſe; The Parliament being the Repreſentatives of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I hope will concur with the Deſires of the King; or, That<pb n="21" facs="tcp:38535:12"/>His Majeſty will acquieſce in what they think, or apprehend agreeable to the Intereſt of Old <hi>England,</hi> or to our Conſtitution, or a probable Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of ſome Settlement: Tho' I cannot pretend to adviſe, give me leave to conclude with the Courtſhip of
<hi>Tully;</hi> which is better than I can make or expreſs.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non tantopere mihi conſiderandum eſt, Quid tu Optimus in</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Praeſentia Velis, quam quid ſemper probaturus ſis.—</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="text">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>IF this prove not ſatisfactory to your Pains in the Peruſal, you are requeſted to believe this Pamphlet was penned in
<hi>Chriſt-mas</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly days, when the Subject-Matter was in a warm Diſpute; and left to a Friend's Diſcretion, whether he would publiſh it, or not. Whilſt this was in Conſideration, the Honourable Houſe of Commons corroborating their Vote for Disbanding the Army to a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Number; my Friend thought fit to lay it aſide, (whilſt I was abſent, by a long Journey.) Nor had I Intentions, ſince my Coming to Town, that it ſhould comeforth, till I had the View of a Book for making the Militia more uſeful: Wherein that Author demonſtrates his having read more of the <hi>Roman</hi> Hiſtory, and their Method, than he has ſeen of the Practical Diſcipline of this Age. Not that I cenſure his Pains: Nor am I fond of the few Propoſitions here inſerted; They are only as an Addition to the Gentleman, who has made the firſt Step towards making the Militia more uſeful. Which Subject, I ſuppoſe, he does not intend to purſue; becauſe he tells us, he is employing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in an Hiſtorical Diſcourſe (in Latin and Engliſh) of <hi>Brutus;</hi> or, <hi>The Hiſtory of Liberty and Tyranny.</hi> I hope this will not be conſtrued that I am Cenſorious; for I really eſteem him a Gentleman of Parts, though I am unknown to him: And will thus far endeavour to join with him in this Work, that if he will allow his Labour to be bring ing of Brick, mine ſhall paſs for Mortar; which others may place, and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as they have more Skill in Raiſing a Superſtructure. I hope we ſhall not be deeply cenſured for endeavouring to enlarge the Acts for the Militia.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:38535:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>I may affirm <hi>Hounſlow</hi> to be a proper Place for Encamping, becauſe I have heard many eminent Officers, who have been much abroad, ſay, no Place in <hi>Europe</hi> admits of better Accommodations, both for freſh Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, and excellent Water; And ſo large an Encampment, that 20000 Men may be ſeen in a Line, upon a dry Flat; and convenient Room for Exerciſe, Wheelings, and Marchings.</p>
            <p>I know there will be two Objections to this Propoſition of
<hi>Houn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlow,</hi> with ſo many Men yearly; <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Charge:
<hi>Secondly,</hi> Long Marches; from <hi>Cornwal, Northumberland, Cumberland,</hi> and the North and South parts of <hi>Wales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt is anſwered by Computation, Whether is eaſier, For the Kingdom to have 20000 Men in Pay, by way of Rotation, for Three Months in the Year; or 20 or 30000 in continual Pay, as a Standing Army. Clothing is the ſame yearly; or elſe they will be a dull and ragged Aſpect in a Camp. And if 20000 Men come every Spring, yearly, freſh Men, and freſh clothed, it will be an Honour to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. And in the Rotation of Four Years, 80000 Men are in Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline. Allow Eight or Ten Weeks for Marching and Encamping 20000 Men; Then allow the old Fourteen Days for Exerciſing thoſe that remain in their Countries for Three Years; That they meet Two or Three Days every Quarter; the whole amounts but to Three Months in the Year. And this, I am confident, will keep their Memories and Motions in Ure.</p>
            <p>And to the other Objection, of long Marches; 'Tis rather a great Help, than otherwiſe, for making Soldiers. One Camp, the farther diſtant from their Native Reſidence, will quicken the Spirits, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh Soldiers, more than Seven Years in their own Country. And as to <hi>Cornwal, &amp;c.</hi> let them march into the Camp a Week later, and march out a Week ſooner than the Body of the Army. And if part of the Guards encamp yearly, they will be a Pattern and Example to the Kingdom in general.</p>
            <p>Many Particles, and little Inſtances, I could have added, which would have ſwelled this Pamphlet beyond the preſent Value. I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wave them, till I ſee how theſe are accepted, or improved; and accordingly, endeavour to make the Courteous Reader better Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; who ſubſcribe my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>His Humble Servant,
<hi>Philo-Patriae.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
